Donald G. Martin Papers VHP2006/10
CCSU Veterans History Project
Donald G. Martin Papers
Bulk, 1944-1946
1944 - 1946, 1950 - 1952, 2005
VHP2006/10
CCSU Veterans History Project
24.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Donald G. Martin as he served in World War II and Korean War with U.S. Navy and U.S. Marine Corps respectively. The collection contains video of an oral history interview, and photographs taken during Korean War.
Martin, Donald G., (Donald Guy), 1926 -
Biographical/Historical note
Donald Martin was drafted into the U.S. Navy in the spring of 1944. He received a specialized training as a navy hospital corpsman. He stationed in the Naval Hospital in Bethesda, MD and then was reassigned overseas to the Navy Military Hospital #204 at Tinian Island. He was discharged as a Pharmacist's Mate 2nd class by the end of May 1946. He then returned to Penn State to continue his studies as an industrial engineer, at which time he also joined a reserve unit. He was called to report for duty in Sept. 1950 and was instead inducted into the Marine Corps as a Staff Sergeant, and went to Field Medical Service School at Camp Lejeune for eight weeks of training. By December of 1950, Martin was in Korea and assigned to the Charlie Medical unit, part of the 1st marine division. He was discharged from the Marine Corps in January of 1952.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Marine Corps. Division, 1st. Medical Battalion, 1st. Company C.; United States. Navy. Military Hospital #204.; United States. Navy.; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Medical care; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Personal narratives, American; United States. Marine Corps -- Medical care; World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Medical care
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/10.I
  - Interview synopsis, Feb. 23, 2006; VHP2006/10.I.1
  - Interview transcript, Feb. 23, 2006; VHP2006/10.I.2
- Series II: Multi-Media, VHP2006/10.II
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/10.II
    - Donald Martin wearing his WWII Navy uniform, when he was a Navy Corpsman. Camp Lejeunen, NC., 1950; VHP2006/10.II.1
    - Donald G. Martin wearing Marine Corps uniform, when he enlisted during the Korean War. Philadelphia, PA, 1950; VHP2006/10.II.2
    - "Charlie Med" (Company C of a medical battalion), 1st Marine Division, on way to Taegu. Mason, Korea, 1950 - 1951; VHP2006/10.II.3
    - "Chow down in muddy mess" Taegu, South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.4
    - Marines in line for rations, Korean town in background. South Korea, 1951; VHP2006/10.II.5
    - "Charlie Med" Personnel. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.6
    - Helicopters and Jeeps bringing in wounded to Charlie Med for medical aid. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.7
    - helicopter bringing in wounded to Charlie Med for medical aid. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.8
    - Helicopter bringing in wounded to Charlie Med for medical aid. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.9
    - Korean village. Wonju, South Korea, 1951; VHP2006/10.II.10
    - Donald Martin in combat gear outside his tent while his company was in reserve. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.11
    - Tents and area while his company was in reserve. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.12
    - Donald Martin’s tent while he was in reserve. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.13
    - Jack Benny performing for USO Camp Shows. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.14
    - USO Camp Shows featuring Frank Remley and Jack Benny. South Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.15
    - Marines artillery, Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.16
    - Intelligence questioning a wounded Chinese prisoner, Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.17
      General note
      Bob Bailey at right was lead corpsman and Donald Martin’s friend from H Company, 3rd Battalion.
    - "the Punchbowl", an extinct volcano valley of military value in the Taebaek Mountains of Korea, 1951; VHP2006/10.II.18
      Don Martin’s company took it without a casualty. The army suffered 32 casualties the day before
    - A Marine patrol in North Korea., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.19
      Donald G. Martin was with this Marine patrol in North Korea. They fired a few rounds from a mortar they carried. They returned to base without any problem
    - Donald G. Martin and other 5 marines at unidentified air field., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.20
      L - R: Top Row: Donald G. Martin, Bob Bailey, Haines (Thomaston, CT) Bottom Row: 3 buddies from Charlie Med All got transferred to Armored Amphibious Bn. in Japan in November or October 1951
    - Donald G. Martin on ship to San Francisco., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.21
    - On ship to San Francisco, going to Treasure Island under the Golden Gate Bridge., 1951; VHP2006/10.II.22
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/10.IIb
    - Oral history interview with Donald G. Martin, Feb. 23, 2006; VHP2006/10.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Vincent, Roche